A Guide to the Giles County (Va.) Business Records, 1836-1912
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Giles County (Va.) Business Records, 1836-1912
Library of Virginia
14 volumes.
Giles County (Va.) Circuit Court
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Many of the business volumes are fragile and should not be handled, please check alternative formats for volumes that have been microfilmed. Please use microfilm if available.
Acquisition Information
These records came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of records from the Giles County Circuit Court in 2010 under accession number 45263, as well as under an undated accession.
Alternative Form Available
Please see Giles County Microfilm index in the Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm available on the Library of Virginia website for full listing.
Branch Bank of Old Dominion Offering Book A, 1857-1865 is available as Giles County (Va.) Microfilm Reel 58.
Historical Information
Context for Record Type: Business Records, both volumes and loose records, are in some cases transferred to the Library of Virginia as components of court record transfers. These business records in some cases were simply stored in the local court building for safe keeping by business owners. In other cases, business records (particularly ledgers, account books, etc.) may have been filed in a court case as an exhibit. These business record exhibits appeared both in chancery causes and in judgments, these records serving as exhibits for business dissolution cases, debut suits, and contract disputes.
Locality History: Giles County was named for William Branch Giles, United States senator from Virginia in 1806 when the county was created from Montgomery, Monroe (now in West Virginia), and Tazewell Counties. Several subsequent additions were made from Wythe (1808), Monroe in 1829 and Mercer in 1841 (both now in West Virginia), Craig (1880), and Tazewell (1826 and 1836) counties. The county seat is Pearisburg.
Scope and Content
Giles County (Va.) Business Records, 1836-1912 is comprised of various records created by individuals and companies in pursuit of documenting business activities in and around Giles County (Va.). Represented records consist of bound volumes of ledgers and an account book.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into four series:
Series I: Business Records of the Branch Bank of Old Dominion, Pearisburg, 1857-1865
Series II: Business Records of Buchanan and Powell, 1902-1912
Series III: Business Records of Ralph M. Stafford and Company, 1861-1874
Series IV: Business Records of an Unidentified Blacksmith, 1836-1838
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Giles County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."
See also: Giles County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1807-1936.
Contents List
- Business Records of the Branch Bank of Old Dominion, Pearisburg 1857-1865, 9 volumes
  Historical Information: The Branch Bank of Old Dominion conducted business in the town of Pearisburg in Giles County, Virginia, during the mid-nineteenth century.
  Scope and Content: The business records of the Branch Bank of Old Dominion, Pearisburg consists of statement books, ledgers, check books, offering books, and letter books.
  - Statement Books 1857-1865
    The statement books record the bank's controlling accounts on a weekly basis from 1857 to 1865. Entries list the name of the account and the amount and amount paid. Accounts include property account, cash account, cost of suits, capital stock, expense account, money due to other banks, profit and loss, and numerous others.
    - Branch Bank of Old Dominion, Pearisburg Statement Book 1857-1860
    - Branch Bank of Old Dominion, Pearisburg 1860-1865
  - Letter Books 1859-1862
    The letter books record the bank's correspondence with account holders, cashiers, and other banks. Information found in letter books relate to the financial activities of the bank including withdrawals, deposits, payments, receipts, and collections. There are also references in some of the correspondence to repeal of a redemption law in Virginia.
    - Branch Bank of Old Dominion, Pearisburg Letter Book 1859-1860
    - Branch Bank of Old Dominion, Pearisburg Bank Letter Book 1860-1862
  - Branch Bank of Old Dominion, Pearisburg Ledgers 1860-1865
    - Branch Bank of Old Dominion, Pearisburg Scratch Ledger 1859-1860
      The ledger recorded financial transactions chronologically on a daily basis. Information found in each entry include name of individual or account, form of payment or receipt, and amount paid or received. Information recorded in the ledger was transferred to General Ledger A, 1857-1865.
    - Branch Bank of Old Dominion, Pearisburg General Ledger A 1857-1865
      The ledger was used to keep track of amounts received from and paid to multiple volumes such as scratch ledgers, check books, blotters, offering books, and journals. It recorded the bank's controlling accounts including cash account, individual deposit account, discount and interest account, bills and notes, capital stock, state securities, Confederate States stocks account, expense account, and others. Transactions listed in each account are listed chronologically. Information found in each transaction include date of transaction, amount paid to volume and amount received from volume. Accounts entries that say "to scratch" or "by scratch" taken from Scratch Ledger, 1860-1865.
    - Branch Bank of Old Dominion, Pearisburg Discount Ledger A 1860-1865
      The ledger recorded the accounts of individual customers. Each account lists financial transactions in chronological order. Entries include page numbers that correlate to a missing journal or ledger.
  - Branch Bank of Old Dominion, Pearisburg Check Book 1857-1860
    The check book recorded financial transactions chronologically on a daily basis. Information found in each entry include name of individual or account, payments received or made by checks or notes, and name of individual to whom check was made or number of note. Information found in check book transferred to General Ledger A, 1857-1865.
    - Branch Bank of Old Dominion, Pearisburg Book-keeper's Check Book 1857-1860
  - Branch Bank of Old Dominion, Pearisburg Offering Book 1857-1865
    The offering book recorded notes offered to the bank for discount. Information found in entries include name of customer, date of transaction, names of endorsers, and amount of transaction.
    - Branch Bank of Old Dominion, Pearisburg Offering Book A 1857-1865
- Business Records of Buchanan and Powell, 1902-1912, 3 volumes
  Historical Information: The firm of Buchanan and Powell operated in Pearisburg, Va., selling a variety of items including ready-made clothing, textiles, household items, groceries, and books. W. H. Buchanan and W. R. Powell were partners in the business.
  Scope and Content: Buchanan and Powell business records, consists of three volumes: Ledger 1(1905-1912), Ledger 2 (1902-1909), and Ledger 3 (1907-1912). The volumes recorded the accounts of individual customers. Entries are organized in chronological order under each customer's name. Information found in each entry includes date, goods purchased or method of payment, quantity of goods purchased, and amounts owed or paid. Merchandise sold included tobacco, clothing, shoes, books, and cloth.
  - Buchanan and Powell Ledger Vol. 1, 1905-1912
  - Buchanan and Powell Ledger Vol. 2, 1902-1909
  - Buchanan and Powell Ledger Vol. 3, 1907-1912
- Business Records of Ralph M. Stafford and Company, 1861-1874, 1 volume.
  Historical Information: Ralph M. Stafford owned a mercantile business at in Giles County, Virginia. He was also a partner in eight additional mercantile businesses located in Giles and Bland counties in Virginia and Mercer and Monroe counties in West Virginia.
  Scope and Content: Ralph M. Stafford and Company Business Records consists of a ledger which recorded the accounts of individual customers. Each account lists in chronological order transactions between the customer and the store. Transaction entries include the following information: date of transaction, goods purchased or method of payment, quantity of goods purchased, amount owed or amount paid. Merchandise sold include soda, food, matches, cookware, dry goods, shoes, cheese, spices, ink, and soap. Payments made by cash, credit, barter (eggs, butter, cheese, and seeds) and labor.
  See also: Giles County Chancery Cause, 1870-002: James Stafford vs. Admr. of Ralph M. Stafford etc.
  - Ralph M. Stafford and Company Ledger, 1861-1874
- Business Records of an Unidentified Blacksmith, 1836-1838, 1 volume.
  Scope and Content: Unidentified Blacksmith Account Book, 1836-1838, recorded the accounts of individual customers. Each account lists transactions in chronological order. Information found in each entry includes the date of transaction, type of transaction, item purchased or service rendered, quantity of items purchased or services rendered, and amount owed or paid.
  - Unidentified Blacksmith Account Book, 1836-1838